Manzanar War Relocation Center records, 1942-1946
UCLA Library Special Collections
Manzanar War Relocation Center records,
1942-1946
122
Manzanar War Relocation Center
68 boxes (34 linear ft.) 39 oversize boxes
The Manzanar War Relocation Center was located in the Owens Valley in Central California. The United States Army initially established the camp as the Owens Valley Reception Center under the management of the Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA), March-May 1942. On June 1, 1942, Manzanar was reconstituted as a War Relocation Authority (WRA) center. Its peak population was 10,121, and the majority of its internees came from pre-World War II Japanese American communities in the Los Angeles basin. The collection consists of files collected and maintained by Ralph Palmer Merritt (Director of the Japanese Relocation Center at Manzanar, California) including files of the Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA), the War Relocation Authority (WRA) records and correspondence from April 1942-December 1945, a history of the Manzanar Center (5 volumes), daily records of the Block Managers, Ralph Merritt's office files, and a two volume index of all evacuees at Manzanar. There are also books, clippings, copies of the Congressional Record, reprints of committee hearings, and magazines documenting the history of Japanese and Japanese Americans in the United States and their internment and military service, photographs and photographic negatives documenting activities and people at Manzanar, and approximately 170 photographs by Ansel Adams of the Manzanar War Relocation Center on 14 x 18 inch mats. The collection also contains copies of various newspapers and printed materials such as the Manzanar Free Press.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF. Advance notice is required for access to the collection. Please contact UCLA Library Special Collections for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ralph Palmer Merritt, 1946.
Funding
Finding aid and digital representations of archival material funded in part by a grant from the Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA).
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922211253606533
History
The Manzanar War Relocation Center was located in the Owens Valley in Central California; the site was used by Paiute-Shoshone Indians for centuries until it became a Euro-American fruit-growing settlement, 1910-35; the United States Army initially established the camp as the Owens Valley Reception Center under the management of the Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA), March-May 1942; on June 1, 1942, Manzanar was reconstituted as a War Relocation Authority (WRA) center; its peak population was 10,121, and the majority of its internees came from pre-World War II Japanese American communities in the Los Angeles basin; Manzanar was declared a state historical landmark in 1972, a national historical landmark in 1985, and a National Historic Site (managed by the National Park Service administration under the United States Department of the Interior) in 1992.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of files collected and maintained by Ralph Palmer Merritt, Director of the Japanese Relocation Center at Manzanar, California. Includes files of the Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA) and the War Relocation Authority (WRA) records and correspondence from April 1942-December 1945. Also includes a history of the Manzanar Center (5 volumes), daily records of the Block Managers, Ralph Merritt's office files, and a two volume index of all evacuees at Manzanar. Books, clippings, copies of the Congressional Record, reprints of committee hearings, and magazines document the history of Japanese and Japanese Americans in the United States and their internment and military service. Approximately 100 photographs and 400 photographic negatives in the collection document activities and people at Manzanar. Includes approximately 170 photographs by Ansel Adams of the Manzanar War Relocation Center on 14 x 18 inch mats. The collection also contains copies of various newspapers and printed materials such as the Manzanar Free Press.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Manzanar War Relocation Center--Archives.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945--Archival resources.; negatives.; Photographs.; Merritt, Ralph Palmer, 1883-1963.; Adams, Ansel, 1902- .
Digitized Items Available Online
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Manzanar War Relocation Center records (354 items).
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project collection of material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Japanese American Research Project - Fading Footsteps of the Issei (Collection 2010). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Items Removed from Collection
Extra copies of publications and printed material about Japanese in the United States, in California, and in the Armed Services, and about Japanese relocation. These have been filed in the California Ephemera Collection (Collection 200). See “Japanese in America.”
The broadsides of the Civilian Exclusion Orders were a gift of the Bancroft Library, 1969, as were the smaller duplicates.
The broadsides are in the Manzanar War Relocation Center records (Collection 122), Portfolio 74, while the duplicate smaller set is filed in the California Ephemera collection (Collection 200). See “Japanese in California.”
Both collections are available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Container List
- War Relocation Authority (WRA): Administrative and Personnel Management Handbooks, Reports
  - Personnel Management Handbook. (Box 1)
  - Administrative Manual. Volume I. (Box 1)
  - Administrative Manual. Volume II. (Box 2)
  - Administrative Manual. Volume III (Finance Handbook). (Box 3)
  - Project Director's Final Report., Feb. 15, 1946.; 5 volumes. (250 + 1592 leaves.) Typescript (carbon). (Box 4)
    - Volume I - Final Report., 250 leaves.; Includes copy of Born Free and Equal, by Ansel Adams. (Box 4)
    - Volume II - Final Sectional Reports. (Box 4)
    - Volume III - Final Sectional Reports. (Box 5)
    - Volume IV - Final Sectional Reports. (Box 5)
    - Volume V - Personal Narratives of Staff Members. (Box 5)
- Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA) - Manzanar File
  Communications, releases, etc. from WCCA filed under the following headings:
  - WCCA: A-Q (Box 6)
    Army
    Canteens - Center Stores
    Clippings (newspapers)
    Community Activities
    Dissolution of the WCCA
    Education
    Employment - recruitment
    Evacuation
    Includes copy of California and Her Less Favored Minorities, by Ruth McKee, prepared for the WRA, April 1944.
    Evacuee Property
    Family Reunion (Information Center). 2 folders.
    Fiscal
    Government
    Housing
    Information Office
    Mess
    Personnel
    Police - Reports, Police Department
    Production - Agriculture and Industry
    Property Control
  - WCCA: R-Z (Box 7)
    Records
    Reports
    Reports - Information Office. March 24, 1942 - April 30, 1942
    Reports - Information Office. May 1942
    Reports - Information Office. June 1942
    Welfare
- War Relocation Authority (WRA) - Manzanar file
  Correspondence, reports, releases, etc. from WRA filed under the following headings:
  - WRA: A-B (Box 7)
    Administration
    Agriculture
    America in the Making
    Army - Army Specialized Training Program (ASTP)
    Auditorium, rules governing
    Bainbridge Island Group
    Bibliography
    Bulletins - Project Director
  - WRA: C (Box 8)
    Camouflage Project
    Cemeteries
    Center Closure
    Community Government. 2 folders.
    Includes Minutes of Block Managers' Meetings, 1942-1943
    Community Government - Advisory Board
  - WRA: C (continued) (Box 9)
    Community Government - Block Managers' Reports, June - December, 1942. 7 folders.
  - WRA: C (continued) (Box 10)
    Community Government - Block Managers' Reports, January-September, 1943. 9 folders.
  - WRA: C (continued) (Box 11)
    Community Government - Block Managers' Reports, October 1943-December, 1944, 1945. 16 folders.
    See Boxes 29-45 for daily reports of block managers.
  - WRA: C-D (Box 12)
    Community Government - History of Internal Government
    A History of Internal Government at Manzanar, by Morris Edward Opler, Community Analyst, Manzanar Relocation Center. March 1942 to December 6, 1942
    Community Government - Manzanar Work Corps & Fair Practices Committee
    Community Government - Manzanar Work Corps & Fair Practices Committee - Candidates
    Community Government - Manzanar Work Corps & Fair Practices Committee - Constitution
    Community Government - Manzanar Work Corps & Fair Practices Committee - Press Releases
    Community Government - Manzanar Work Corps & Fair Practices Committee - Report
    Community Government - Negotiating Committee (Committee of 108)
    Community Government - Town Hall Bulletins
    Conferences
    Confidential, Miscellaneous letters
    Co-op - Financial Statements
    Co-op - Memo of Understanding - Manzanar Free Press
    Co-op - Miscellaneous papers re: development
    Court Decisions
    Department of Justice
  - WRA: E (Box 13)
    Education (Publications)
    Employment
    Engineering
  - WRA: F-G (Box 14)
    Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI)
    Fire Protection
    Fiscal - Script, Issuance of; Appropriations, etc.; Budget
    Free Press (Manzanar)
    Guayule Reports, 1942-1945 & Final Report. 3 folders.
  - WRA: H-J (Box 15)
    Honda Family records - 6 folders.
    Hospital
    Housing, evacuee
    Industry
    International Relations - Geneva Treaty, Red Cross Messages, etc.
    International Relations - The Repatriate - Expatriate Group of Manzanar, by Morris E. Opler, Community Analyst, Manzanar Relocation Center.
    International Relations - Repatriation and Expatriation
    International Relations - Spanish Consul
    Investigations - Senator Chandler
    Investigations - Dies, Martin & Committee
    Investigations - Ford, Leland
    Investigations - Mulvey
    Investigations - Jack B. Tenny
    Investigations - Tolan Committee
    Investigations - Webster
    Issei
    Japanese organizations, holidays, etc.
  - WRA: K-L (Box 16)
    Kibei
    Kibei - Hearings
    Kibei - Nisei Study
    Language - Lexicon of Center Terms
    Law and Order
    Law and Order - Incident - Administration of Center
    Law and Order - Incident - Death Valley Group
    Law and Order - Incident - Events leading up to and including incident - August 1942 - December 21, 1942
    Law and Order - Incident - Events leading up to and including incident - December 21, 1942
    Law and Order - Incident - Moab
  - WRA: L-M (Box 17)
    Law and Order - Incident - Persons involved, miscellaneous papers on
    Law and Order - Incident - Press Releases
    Law and Order - Judicial Committee
    Law and Order - Peace Committee
    Law and Order - Project Director's Court
    Manzanar, description of
    Manzanar - Citizens Federation
    Manzanar - Early Days
    Manzanar - Lease
    Manzanar - Transfer from WCCA to WRA
    Memorials to Manzanar Servicemen
    Merritt, Ralph P. - Scrapbook items, 1942 - 1943 - 3 folders.
  - WRA: M (continued) (Box 18)
    Merritt, Ralph P. - Scrapbook items, 1944 - 1946 5 folders.
    Merritt, Ralph P. - Speeches of, etc. - 2 folders.
    Mess Division
    Mess Division - Mess Hall Workers Association
    Military Police
    Motor Pool
    Meyer, Dillon S. - Director's Speeches
  - WRA: N-P (Box 19)
    Nisei
    Project Attorney
    Project Attorney - Legal Aid Office
    Project Director - Personnel
    Project Director - Speeches by
    See also Merritt file.
    Public Relations - Center Publications - Manuscripts, typescript carbons
    Public Relations - Center Publications - Newspapers
    Public Relations - Center Publications - Pamphlets or bound publications
    Public Relations - Evacuation, articles on
    Public Relations - Evacuation, publications on - Ansel Adams
  - WRA: P (continued) (Box 20)
    Public Relations - Articles on Japanese-Americans - Clippings
    Public Relations - Articles on Japanese-Americans - Magazines, pamphlets, etc., 1943 - 1944
    Public Relations - Articles on Japanese-Americans - Magazines, pamphlets, etc., 1945 - 1946
    Public Relations - Articles on Japanese-Americans - Manuscripts and mimeographs
    Public Relations - Clippings (newspapers) - 3 folders.
    Public Relations - Correspondence re: news accounts
  - WRA: P-R (Box 21)
    Public Relations - Committees on Fair Play, Civil Liberties, etc.
    Public Relations - Japan re: attitudes towards Nisei
    Public Relations - Mailing lists, letters, etc.
    Public Relations - Miscellaneous
    Public Relations - Nisei in Uniform
    Public Relations - State and County
    Public Relations - State, County, etc. Coordinating Committees
    Public Safety and Health Committee
    Regional Office - Circulars (#1-93)
  - WRA: R (continued) (Box 22)
    Regional Office - Circulars (dup. set #1-92)
    Regional Office - San Francisco
    Relocation - 1942
    Relocation - January - June, 1943 - Correspondence, memos, etc.
    Relocation - July - December, 1943 & undated - Correspondence, memos, etc.
    Relocation - 1943 - Printed material
  - WRA: R (continued) (Box 23)
    Relocation - 1944
    Relocation - 1944 - A Study of Change of Answer Cases at Manzanar, by M. E. Opler, Community Analyst. April 3, 1944. - 88 leaves. Typescript (carbon). 2 copies.
    Relocation - 1945
    Relocation - Leave Clearance Hearings
    Relocation - Leave procedures, furloughs, etc.
    Relocation - Offices
    Relocation - Registration, 1942 - April 1943
    Relocation - Registration, May - December 1943
    Relocation - Registration, 1944 - 1945
  - WRA: R (continued) (Box 24)
    Relocation - Registration, Army and leave clearance, Confidential, June 1943
    Relocation - Volunteers
    Reports - Chapman
    Reports - Final, preparation of
    Reports - Project (Reports Office): June - October, 1942 - 5 folders.
  - WRA: R (continued) (Box 25)
    Reports - Project (Reports Office): November 1942 - January 1944 - 15 folders.
  - WRA: R (continued) (Box 73*)
    Reports - Project (Reports Office): February 1944 - September 1945 - 19 folders.
    *[formerly Box 25a]
  - WRA: R-S (Box 26)
    First Quarterly Report. March 18 to June 30, 1942 - Mimeograph. 2 copies.
    Second Quarterly Report. July 1 to September 30, 1942 - Mimeograph. 2 copies.
    Quarterly Report. October 1 to December 31, 1942 - Mimeograph. 2 copies.
    Semi-Annual Report. January 1 to June 30, 1943 - Mimeograph. 2 copies.
    Semi-Annual Report. January 1 to June 30, 1944 - Mimeograph. 1 copy.
    Miscellaneous. - 2 items.
    Roosevelt, Franklin D. - Statement on Americanism - Broadside.
    Segregation - General - Correspondence, memos
    Segregation - General - Statements and Releases
    Segregation - General - Studies of Segregants at Manzanar, by M. Opler. - vii, 130 leaves. Typescript (carbon)
    Segregation - Tule Lake - Employment Breakdown of Workers Scheduled For Segregation to Tule Lake, September 15, 1943.
    Segregation - Tule Lake - Segregation Roster - 2 copies.
  - WRA: S-U (Box 27)
    Segregation - Handbook
    Segregation - Handbook - Bulletins, schedules, etc.
    Segregation - Hearings
    Segregation - Responsibility of Army
    Segregation - Train Commander, instructions to (A. T. Williams)
    Solicitor's Validity of Detention - 2 copies.
    Statistics
    Un-American Activities
  - WRA: U-Z (Box 28)
    U.S.O.
    Visitors - Soldiers
    War Relocation Authority - Centers
    War Relocation Authority, memo of agreement with War Department
    War Relocation Authority, principle of
    Welfare - Religion
    Welfare - YWCA, etc.
    Western Defense Command - Army Hearings
    Western Defense Command - Proclamations
- Manzanar Relocation Center - Daily reports of block managers to Town Hall, 1942-1944; See also: Box 11, for Block Manager reports.
  Includes minutes of block meetings.
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, July-Aug., 1942; 7 folders. (Box 29)
    See also Box 45.
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Sept.-Oct., 1942; 9 folders. (Box 30)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Nov.-Dec., 1942; 6 folders. (Box 31)
    See also Box 45
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Jan.-Feb., 1943; 7 folders. (Box 32)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Feb.-April, 1943; 7 folders. (Box 33)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, April-June, 1943; 7 folders. (Box 34)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, June-July, 1943; 7 folders. (Box 35)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, July-Aug., 1943; 7 folders. (Box 36)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Sept.-Oct., 1943; 6 folders. (Box 37)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Oct.-Nov., 1943; 6 folders. (Box 38)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Nov.-Dec., 1943; 7 folders. (Box 39)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Dec. 1943-Jan. 1944; 6 folders. (Box 40)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, Jan.-Feb., 1944; 6 folders. (Box 41)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, March-April, 1944; 6 folders. (Box 42)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, April-May, 1944; 7 folders. (Box 43)
  - Block Managers - Daily Reports, May-Aug., 1944; 8 folders. (Box 44)
  - Miscellaneous Block Managers Daily Reports, July-Nov. 1942; 2 folders. (Box 45)
  - Daily Reports from Town Hall, June 1942; July 1942; 9 folders. (Box 45)
  - [no further description available], Sept. 1942; April, 1943; Jan.-May, 1944 (Box 45)
- Manzanar Relocation Center - Town Hall Records
  - Block Managers Assembly - Minutes, November 1943 - October 1945 (Box 46)
  - Block Managers - Resignation and appointments of. (Box 46)
  - Change of Block Managers - Memos. (Box 46)
  - Community activities. (Box 46)
  - Community activities - Cooperative association. (Box 46)
  - Community activities - Cooperative association (F. Yasuda). (Box 46)
  - Community fund. (Box 46)
  - Cooperative enterprises - Mr. Frank Yasuda. (Box 46)
  - Coordinating Counsel Meeting, November -December 1944 (Box 46)
  - Letters of Appreciation (from Town Hall). (Box 46)
  - Personnel - Block Managers committees, etc. (Box 46)
  - Personnel Department. (Box 46)
  - Private Enterprise - list. (Box 46)
  - Property Owners Delegates. (Box 46)
  - Register for meeting. (Box 46)
  - Requests and inquiries from residents. (Box 46)
  - Segregation. (Box 46)
  - Soldiers addresses. (Box 46)
  - Soldiers who left from Manzanar - list. (Box 46)
  - U.S.O. (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous - Spanish Consul visit, future policy, etc. (Box 46)
- Ralph P. Merritt (Project Director) Office file
  - Diary (office) as kept by Mrs. Hooper. (Box 47)
  - Gila River Project, Rivers, Arizona. Legislative manual. (Box 47)
  - Manzanar Inventory, November 15, 1945.; Black notebook. (Box 47)
  - Manzanar - maps and plans. (Box 47)
  - Manzanar - scripts and songs. (Box 47)
  - Manzanar - scripts and songs, Carbon copy. (Box 47)
  - Correspondence, memos, etc. - unsorted. (Box 48)
  - Official WRA Releases. (Box 48)
  - Statements (addresses) re: Japanese, relocation, etc., by various people, various dates (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and articles. (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous reports, mostly project related. (Box 48)
  - Merritt, “letter to myself for future reference.”, Dec. 1951; 2 leaves. Carbon. (Box 48)
- Far Eastern Propaganda Analysis files
  - Propaganda Analysis Files, June, July, September - November 1943; 5 folders. (Box 49)
  - Special Reports - “Restricted”, 1 folder (22 items). (Box 49)
  - Propaganda Analysis Files, July - November 1944; 4 folders. (Box 50)
  - Propaganda Analysis Files, December 1944 - April 1945; 5 folders. (Box 51)
  - Propaganda techniques, April 1945; 1 folder.
  - Propaganda Analysis Files, May - September 1945; 5 folders. (Box 52)
- Alphabetical file of newspaper clippings re: WRA, Manzanar, etc.
  - Newspaper Clippings: A - M (Box 53)
    Army - Nisei in service
    Books on WRA matters
    Churches
    Columnists - National
    Congressional action
    Deportation, repatriation, etc.
    Editorials, general
    Elections, politics
    Exclusion orders - Army ban, etc.
    Farm & Agriculture
    Feature Articles of importance
    Flipinos, Mexicans, & other minorities
    Housing for Japanese-Americans
    Incidents, other areas
    Incidents, Southern California area
    Jobs for Japanese-Americans
    Legal cases and laws
    Legion, VFW, etc.
    Letters to editors
    Masuda, Mary
    Myer, Dillon S
  - Newspaper Clippings: O - Z, unsorted (Box 54)
    Officials - Govt., etc. - Atty. General Clark, etc.
    Opposition and Criticism - Lechner, etc.
    Prisoners of War
    Releases from centers
    Social Welfare
    Speeches and Meetings
    Spy Case Publicity (including films)
    Statistical Data
    Storage of Property
    Miscellaneous - unsorted
- Manzanar Relocation Center - Numbered photographic negatives and prints
  - Numbered photographic negatives, Over 400 miscellaneous views of Manzanar, from the construction of the camp to its destruction. Contact prints are included with many of the negatives. (Box 55)
  - Notebook, Index to subjects of numbered negatives, prepared by Robert L. Brown, Assistant Project Director, Feb. 1946. (Box 56)
  - Prints, Miscellaneous prints made from negatives in Box 55.; 3 folders. (Box 56)
- Manzanar Relocation Center - War Relocation Authority photographs
  - War Relocation Authority photographs. Midland Savings Building, Denver, Colorado., ca. 90 photographs.; Mainly of Japanese who were at Manzanar, showing their activities and life after leaving the Relocation Center. Includes 60 8"×10" glossy photographs. Some of these duplicate the larger mounted photographs. Most are marked for inclusion in a publication. Photographs from Boxes 65-67 exhibited in "Two Views of Manzanar" at the Frederick Wight Gallery, UCLA, November 1978-1979 (Box 65-67)
    - View southwest over Manzanar., 1-; 95
    - Burning leaves, autumn morning., 2-; 91
    - Manzanar street scene., 3-; 178
    - High school recess period., 4-; 181
    - Packing bus., 5-; 161
    - Hog farm., 6-; 176
    - Chicken farm, Mori Nakashima., 7-; 226
    - Line crew at work., 8-; 169
    - Roy Takeno in front of Free Press office., 9-; 83
    - Relocations bulletin board., 10-; 6
    - Desk of Roy Takeno, Manzanar FreePress., 11-; 88
    - Nurse Aiko Hamaguchi and Francis Yokoyama in nursery ofhospital., 12-; 22
    - Dressmaking class, Mrs. Ryhe Yoshizawa., 13-; 70
    - Mrs. Ryhe Yoshizawa's dressmaking class., 14-; 75
    - In co-op store., 15-; 145
    - The "Jive Bombers"., 16-; 121
    - Benji Iguchi with squash crop., 17-; 30
    - Mr. & Mrs. Dennis Shimizu., 18-; 103
    - Yonemitsu family: Michael Koichi, Franci Koji, Lucy Toshiko., 19-; 37
    - Mr. & Mrs. Toyo Miyatake and family., 20-; 173
    - Toy Takeno addressing Town Hall meeting., 21-; 84
    - Mr. & Mrs. Richard Izuno and children., 22-; 172
    - Social life in co-op store, 6 March 1942., 23-; 148
    - Detail, high school play., 24-; 163
    - Rose Fukuda and Roy Takeda., 25-; 174
    - San Bozono, policeman., 26-; 115
    - Tatsuo Miyake, divinitystudent., 27-; 96
    - Miss Kay Fukuda, cadet nurse, U.S.N.C.N. Corps., 28-; 99
    - Koyoharu Anzai & Roy M. Takeno at Town Hallmeeting., 29-; 85
    - Ryohe Nojima, farmer., 30-; 32
    - Mori Nakashima, poultryexpert., 31-; 112
    - Yonehisa Yamagami,electrician., 32-; 105
    - Pvt. Margaret Fukuoka, W.A.C., 33-; 106
    - Cpl. Jimmie Shohara., 34-; 10
    - Cpl. Shohara's ribbons., 35-; 11